Okay, so to begin,
we are today's דף daf is מ״ו Mem Vav 46, but we're
still a little bit behind, and we begin with the משנה Mishnah
on מ״ה עמוד ב׳. Mem Heh Amud Bet. So let's take a
look. So people were very interested in their hand in this thing.
Here's definitely going to be a challenging משנה. Mishnah. So it's about
race, or at least that's one of them. Let's take a look.
הכושי HaKushi Ethiopian, so it's not just about dark skin, but it's
clearly, you know, sort of even if something is completely natural for
that person's race, it's not considered to be natural within, you know,
where most כהנים Kohanim are. That seems to be at least if
not a מום, mum, it's in the category of זרעו של אהרן,
zaro shel Aharon, שוה בזרעו של אהרן, shaveh bezaro shel Aharon, like
with this, you know, what's common or the most, you know, whatever,
you know, the middle of the bell-shaped curve. Moses' children.
Well, yeah, good thing that they were לויים, Leviim, not כהנים. Kohanim.
Maybe they took after their father. Yeah, it's true. הגיחור, Hagichor, which
you'll see what that means in the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא Gemara basically
will say that it means somebody either that is reddish complexion, like
or maybe somebody that's albino, whitish. והלבקן, Vehalavkan, also that's the whitish
complexion, tell you albino. והקיפח והננס, Vehakipeach vehananas, the קיפח kipeach and
the ננס nanas we'll see what that is,
like probably means that like a giant as opposed to the ננס
nanas which is the midget. והחרש והשוטה. Vehacherish vehashoteh. Now here we
also get very interesting because again we've already seen that not all
these are physical issues like the other day about asthma and epilepsy.
So here we have the deaf-mute and the person who is the
שוטה, shoteh, which is, you know, more like mentally unstable, they say
insane. It's a brain, yeah.
Insane is more like of a
legal term, although there's also legal term, but you know in the
גמרא Gemara it's somebody that really is maybe we would today say
like schizophrenic, seems to be sometimes what's being described, somebody who really
does not, is not fully aware of their surrounding reality.
There're discussions about the exact parameters of שוטה shoteh in the גמרא
Gemara in חגיגה. Chagigah. והשיכור, Vehashikor, somebody who's drunk. Now all of
these things, got drunk actually is a question, is that a separate
פסול pasul for עבודה? avoda? So the גמרא Gemara will talk about
this. Independent alcohol. Drunk, right, but
not separate invalidity. גמרא Gemara says that a כהן Kohen is not
allowed to drink wine or be inebriated when they work, so it's
not, doesn't belong in this category, that's a separate exclusion. Even if
he's an alcoholic? No, that doesn't seem to be. So anyway, but
we'll see about that in the גמרא, Gemara, but the point seems
to be similar to the point about epilepsy, that things that would
be visible through the person's actions although not a physical characteristic are
included in this category. That seems to be the common denominator. ובעלי
נגעים טהורים, Uva'alei nega'im tehorim, if a person had a spot of
leprosy even if they're not leprous because that would obviously then if
they were actually מצורע metzora they couldn't be in the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, they couldn't be on הר הבית. Har HaBayis. But let's
say it's a spot but technically it doesn't make them טמא, tamei,
nevertheless it's a disfigurement and that would be a problem.
So פסולים באדם, psulim ba'adam, all of these are invalid for humans
וכשרים בבהמה, ukesherim babehema, not a problem for animals. That seems to
be the bookend of the opening משנה. Mishnah. The opening משנה Mishnah
said that there are things in which humans have greater invalidities than
animals. The way the גמרא Gemara conceptualized it was that it's not
a concept of מום, mum, of a blemish, but a concept of
שוה בזרעו של אהרן, shaveh bezaro shel Aharon, that it has to
be that this is sort of what you know is most common
or it's not particularly uncommon amongst כהנים. Kohanim. And that is distinctive
of a problem by כהנים. Kohanim. If it's not a מום mum
it's not a problem by animals. So therefore this line seems to
be the bookend of the opening line of the פרק, perek, not
just about the things that we just mentioned. All of these things
are problems for כהנים, Kohanim, not problem for animals because they are
not technically מומים mumim although we actually did have a few מומים
mumim along the way. Things about the eyes, things about the arms,
things that were specifically relating to פסוקים psukim in the תורה. Torah.
But nevertheless the majority if not all of these, but certainly the
majority, are specific to humans.
When they say red, they don't mean red hair, they mean red
skin.
Skin, skin, I said complexion, yeah. רבי חנינא אומר, Rabbi Chanina omer,
שוטה מן הבהמה אינה מן המובחר. shoteh min habehema einah min hamuvchar.
It's not good to have an animal that's of that's you know
that's crazy. Again there's going to be about what whether or not
mentally sound because maybe also that's like is this an appropriate gift?
It's funny of course you're שוחט-ing shochet it and presenting it at
the moment before you שוחט shochet it. It's funny because it actually
it gets sanctified earlier but the actual moment that starts becoming really
fully status of a קרבן korban is when you שוחט shochet it.
So it depends, but anyway certainly the שחיטה shechita elevates its level
and so on so you'd think at that moment who cares whether
it was you know what its mental state was? But presumably because
until that moment you know maybe it's also the fact that you're
giving also God the cast-offs. Like I can't do anything with this
animal, it's a שוטה, shoteh, I can't use it, I can't do
anything, I'll just give it as a קרבן. korban. So maybe it
affects
it.
Although some of the physical characteristics still visible, but you're right, not
in anywhere near the same degree as when it's alive. So, and
right, so it is interesting that of all the things that we
mentioned, this is the one that he singles out as something that's
not ideal for a
קרבן. Korban. רבי אליעזר אומר אף בעלי הדילדולין פסולין באדם וכשרים בבהמה.
Rabbi Eliezer Omer af Ba'alei Hadildulin psulin ba-adam u-kesherim ba-behema. There's a
final category of the, I think about the hanging skin or the,
you know, lumps of skin that are coming off, that those are
problems by humans and not by בהמה. behema. We did have that
before and it's funny that it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying it
because presumably everybody agrees that it's a problem, that it's a problem
by humans. Although, I mean, there was a debate by the hunchback
and so on, so it's not exactly clear. Is he adding that
they're כשר kasher by בהמה? behema? Yeah, not exactly clear and what
he's adding. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
I think you mentioned about someone being so tall?
Yeah, but let's take a look. I understand. Let's take a look
at the
גמרא. Gemara. כושי אוכמא, Cushi Uchma, black skin. גיחור חיורא, Gichor Chivra,
white skin. לבקן סומקא, Lavkhan Sumka, red skin. Which is funny because
you would think לבקן lavkhan is like לבן, lavan, so the גמרא's
Gemara going to reverse it anyway. איני, Eini, is that really true?
והא דאמר להו, Ve-ha de-amar le-hu, there was this person that was
saying מאן בעי לוקייני, Man bai lukiani, who wants some לוקייני, lukiani,
ואשתכח חיורא, ve-ishtachach chivra, presumably some sheep that are לוקייני lukiani and
what was he and found that he was selling particularly white sheep.
אלא, Ela, not exactly clear what was white. רש״י Rashi says sheep.
Anyway, אלא כושי אוכמא, ela Cushi Uchma, fine, כושי Cushi is black.
גיחור סומקא, Gichor Sumka, גיחור Gichor is red. כדאמרי אינשי, Ki-de-amri inshi,
like people say, סומקא גיחייא, Sumka gichaya, people when they talk about
red things sometimes referred to as גיחייא. gichaya. So going by the
Aramaic vernacular to explain the phrase in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, and
לבקן Lavkhan is חיורא, chivra, is white. כההוא דאמר להו, Ke-hahu de-amar
le-hu, like the case we just quoted, מאן בעי לוקייני ואשתכח חיורא.
man bai lukiani ve-ishtachach chivra. Somebody was selling לוקייני lukiani and it
was found out that they were selling white sheep. So here you
get again, now obviously for us with our, you know, high sensitivity
to racial issues, appropriately so, because of the way that different races
have been, you know, have been enslaved and otherwise, you know, and
otherwise, you know,
mistreated and and what's the word I'm looking for? Anyway, whatever. Thank
you, that's another good word. Anyway, that are sensitive to this, you
know, is it conceptually, you know, bracketing out, which is not easy
to bracket, is conceptually more challenging than the idea of like lefties,
you know, or like others. But I guess the difference is that
yes, in all of these things it's just picking people that are
within some random distribution of the population and saying that because they're
not like us, like a narrowly defined us, you know, they're considered
not שווה בזרעו של אהרן. shaveh be-zaro shel Aharon. But again, I
think the difference is that yes, lefties and people without outie belly
buttons or whatever, you know, might be ten percent of the population,
but they're a randomly distributed ten percent and it's not so visible
and it doesn't have the history of, you know, persecution and enslavement
and all those other types of issues. So I do think that
that's why, given that background, it makes this, although in a certain
way it's completely consistent with everything that's being been said until now,
but for us, I think it resonates very, like, differently, this issues
around race. Did you want to say something?
Could a כהן kohen marry a כושי? Cushi? I'm sorry? Could a
כהן kohen marry...
yeah, these are no problems about marrying or it's just a and
even a כהן kohen who
has... yeah, what what would it even come to be? Oh right,
that's a good point. Or maybe if a כושי Cushi converted then
they're not going to be a כהן. kohen. Right. What? Child?
Yeah, well that's...
well כהנים Kohanim don't marry a גר. geir. Well right, so, so
גר, geir, so that's a good point. So כהן kohen marrying a
גר, geir, if somebody converts under three years old, then then that's
debateable we basically פוסקין poskin that that's not a problem for a
כהן kohen to marry a גר. geir. But you're right, it's a
good point. I mean, you know, I guess if כהנים Kohanim spent
some of these things are affected by by geography, right? Like if
people spend a very long time or is that just because those
also lead to intermarriage cases? Like Jews that come from, you know,
from Yemen look very different, right, than Jews that come from Germany.
You know, is that because just geography or is it also because
of intermarriage? But, but anyway, but that's a very good point too.
Unless, I mean, I know you could understand and say just a
genetic... I mean at whatever...
even the red
one.
Right. Yeah.
There's a tribe of Africans in South Africa that claim to be
descendants of Jews and they all have the כהן kohen or most
have the כהן kohen genetic marker. Very, very interesting. And and their
tradition is they were descendants of priests who fled with one of
the after one of the persecutions. Wow, very interesting. And they look
like black Africans.
Wait, so what I want to understand is, is what I think
you'd said this before, is this in a place where most of
the כהנים, Kohanim, let's say, are white and then you have a
black כהן? kohen? Or would this be geography related? Let's say you're
in Africa and then you have a white כהן, kohen, that'd be
a מום. mum.
Yeah, I know. גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss. Right, I understand. גמרא... Gemara...
assuming, you're right, like a basically white, or even prob—it's funny actually,
we think it's assuming white like us, probably for the גמרא Gemara
was assuming more swarthy, more Semitic, I don't know. Yeah,
we might be white, who knows? I just said the גמרא Gemara
was albino, maybe we're too white anyway, you know, who knows? But
yeah, I don't know. The גמרא Gemara is assuming the entire population
of כהנים Kohanim are one thing. It does not discuss the question
about regional, you know, differences. So I don't know the
other way either.
Yeah, although I don't—I think the גמרא Gemara is assuming that we
look at the entire class.
But I don't—I'm sorry, what do you mean by that?
We don't—we look at all the כהנים, Kohanim, you know, but even
we look at all of them, and if they are still an
outlier percentage within the entire class of כהנים, Kohanim, we'd be—I'm assuming
we're not looking at regional differences. We're trying to universalize.
Meaning, if all African כהנים Kohanim then, let's say, compared to the
כהנים Kohanim anyway, would be פסול pasul as כהנים?
Kohanim? Right, unless they made—wound up making up like a significant percentage
of all of the כהנים Kohanim in the world. That's my guess
about what the גמרא's Gemara approach is. Isaac, did you want to
say something?
Yeah, I know we've discussed this constantly, but I just can't let
it pass because it's a tremendous theological problem, I believe, that we
are saying that God prefers—that the epitome of creation is the white,
learned male. Learned wasn't here exactly, but okay. Male definitely, but white.
And everything
else—and so they are giving us standards of perfection which becomes internalized.
All these ישיבה yeshiva students from very young who learn all this,
it's—it becomes internalized and this superiority, which affects הלכה. halacha. We see
here, this is—it's not just
talking theoretically.
This is complete הלכה. halacha. So, so we yet live with these
are the הלכות halachot that shape our lives. And what do we
do? At the heart of it is this theology.
Look, I totally agree with you. I—the best I can come to—well,
first of all, in terms of how much it gets internalized, I
mean, you know, בכורות Bechorot is a rarely learned מסכת. masechet. But
that doesn't—But it's all over the גמרא. Gemara. This attitude
permeates—The concept of מום, mum, the concept of מום mum is definitely
on every דף, daf,
although again,
the one thing the גמרא Gemara did to somewhat—And the superiority, right,
and the superiority of boys
versus girls, I don't want to say all, but boys should learn
that this is the
epitome of—Look, I don't—I don't disagree with—with any of that. I, you
know, the best I personally, I struggle with that as well a
great deal, you know, also very personally affects me because my kids
who are not, you know, who have special needs and so on.
The best I can try to come into terms with it is
as I said, first of all, I think it's an amazing thing
that the רמבם Rambam sort of reverses, but the גמרא, Gemara, you
know, sort of redefines almost everything in this פרק perek as not
being an actual מום. mum. Now, that doesn't solve the problem, but
it makes it somewhat better. We're not calling it a blemish, we're
just acknowledging that it's not the, you know, not the majority of
כהנים Kohanim are like this. But again, I'm not saying that solves
it at all, but it somewhat makes it a little less severe.
And the other thing which is that I said, which is that,
you know, personally I try to understand this in the context of
the whole aesthetics and the visuals of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
and that this is a piece with that. But I agree with
you, that's not a real solution because it's, you know, even if
you say that sometimes we have to deal with people's, you know,
with people's limitations and make concessions to human nature because—but you still
want to be dealing with a corrective at the same time. If
you see it as problematic, right, so you can't, you know, you
can't completely ignore where people are at and say here's the ideal
way to worship God, all this other stuff is נארישקייט. narishkeit. You
know, it's like what the רמבם Rambam says about קרבנות, korbanot, you
could, but you won't get anywhere. So to some degree you have
to understand that people
like—many people or most people demand a certain aesthetics. But the problem
is, well, where are you working at the corrective at the same
time when you're trying to make those concessions because you need to
bring people in and give them a way to access from where
they're at, where are you also trying to teach the corrective of
that so that it doesn't become internalized as an ideal? And to
that I really don't have an answer. So I really—I, you know,
I really agree with—with everything you raised.
Just on another point, the way you formulate it,
theology is handed down and it affects the way we—we trans—we pass
on our tradition, but the way I see it, you know, it's
not a vacuum, it's circular. I mean, where did these rules come
from? It came from a certain view of—of one's own culture, one's
own ethnic group and so on. You know what I'm saying?
But look at Israel today where ספרדי Sephardic kids aren't allowed in
certain—Right, right.
But you see it came from this mind here?
I think it comes from the attitude that permeates every דף daf
of—That there are certain hierarchies.
It permeates that we adopt theology to human attitude.
But the תורה—But Torah the point is that it—the point is that
it finds places to be reinforced rather than to be critiqued within
the system. That's Chris's point. Right, right, right.
I just have such אנגסט angst for you because we go through
everything cultural, we go through,
you have to represent the piece being that sympathizes with women, with
blacks, with whites, with yellows, and and you know these sages, they
didn't sit there and worry about any of this stuff. On they
went.
But,
but halakhic Judaism has to grapple with it. Absolutely. Absolutely.
Yes, it does. Right. I agree. I agree. But point taken.
It's alright, thank you. But okay, so but no, I think that
those are really on the mark.
One more technical question. You used the term פסולין. psulin. Right.
It doesn't say that these are מומים. mumim.
Well right, and before it did use, it did use מומים mumim
more liberally before it used פסול. psul. But again, the point I'm
making is that the גמרא Gemara tries to make almost every case
in these משניות Mishnayot a פסול psul and not a מום, mum,
this new category of זרע של אהרן. zara shel aharon. Okay. But
the רמב"ם Rambam actually ignores that categorization. He acknowledges a separate category
but he calls it a different type of מום. mum. He says
it's a מום, mum, מום שאינו שוה בבהמה ובאדם. mum she'eino shaveh
b'vhemah u'v'adam.
Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. קיפח, Kipei'ach,
what is that? תני רב זביד: Tanei Rav Zevid: גבוה, gavo'ah, a
very tall. Okay, which as, as Michael pointed out, is what we
said that משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu was, was ten feet tall, so
ten אמות amot tall. So let's take a look at what the
גמרא Gemara does with this.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says איני, eini, is this really true? ותני
רבי אבהו: Ve'tanei Rabbi Abbahu: מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא משתבח בבעלי קומה?
minayin she'hakadosh baruch hu mishtabei'ach b'va'alei komah? How do we know that
God
praises himself
through the people of stature, giants? שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as the verse says:
ואנכי השמדתי את האמורי מפניהם, ve'anochi hishmadti et ha'emori mifneihem, I have
wiped out the Amorites from, from, from in front of you and
you came into conquer the land of Israel, אשר כגובה ארזים גבהו,
asher kegovah arazim govho, that they were as tall as the cedars.
So you see being tall is a great thing. So אמר רב
פפא: amar Rav Papa: באריכא שמיטא סניא. bearicha shemita sania. No, what
do we talk when we say that tall is a problem, it
means it's tall and and very thin, like a beanpole. You know,
you ever seen in the Ripley's Believe It or Not, like those,
you know, super tall people, super, whatever. Anyway, I remember reading that
as a kid. Right. So those super super thin tall people, those
are, those are like the, you know, that's like considered to be
a not visually pleasant type of a thing and therefore that is,
that is what is invalid.
But somebody that is normally proportioned and tall, that would not be
a problem. That would have been משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. What? משה
רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu as a regular אמה. amah. Right, that was in
my mind, that was like really strong. Right,
exactly. All right, so now this brings
up the question, how could משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu have performed the
עבודה? avodah?
Well, that's what we just said, is that he was normally proportioned,
he wasn't a beanpole. Only the beanpole is invalid. All right, move
on. God, guys, we're let's get more than one דף daf behind.
Okay.
אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Resh Lakish: גבוה, gavo'ah, now talking, the גרסא
girsa of גמרא, Gemara, awareness of certain genetics of before Mendel, was
Mendel, right? With the with the anyway, okay. גבוה לא ישא גבוהית,
gavo'ah lo yisa gavo'hit, a very tall man should not marry a
very tall woman, שמא יצא מהן תורן, shema yetzei meihen toren, that
the child will be like a, I say beanpole, it says a
mast, you know, on a ship, like a ship's mast, essentially like
a beanpole, super tall and thin, you know, will just multiply the
effect.
You mean specifically a very tall and inproportionally tall?
No, I don't know. Anyway, the point is that you'll have a
multiplier effect, okay? If you have two tall people marrying, the child
will be super tall.
אמר Amar and therefore
ננס לא ישא ננסת, nannas lo yisa nannaset, a midget should not
marry a female midget, שמא יצא מהן אצבעי, shema yetzei meihen etzba'i,
maybe you'll have a Tom Thumb that emerges.
אצבעי, Etzba'i, somebody the size of a finger.
לבן לא ישא לבנה, Lavan lo yisa levana, a white person should
not marry another white person, שמא יצא מהן בוהק, shema yetzei meihen
bohak, maybe you'll have an albino. So there you see, you're supposed
to have, right, interracial marriage, so you should not come out with
a translucent skin. Let me just finish this one by, שחור לא
ישא שחורה, shachor lo yisa sh'chora, a dark-skinned or black-skinned should not
marry another dark-skinned person. You see, I don't think they were talking
about them as a race here, they were talking about people within
the normal outliers within within a within their normal like white or
Mediterranean complexion, שמא יצא מהן תפוח, shema yetzei meihen tapu'ach,
let's because the they will emerge will be somebody who will be
as black as a pot, you know, super dark black. So you
don't want to marry somebody like you in this regard because that's
going to have a multiplier effect. And maybe by the way, this
also ties into the גמרא Gemara acknowledging this reality of or whatever,
you know, how they understood the impact about the parents, so on,
you know, the גמרא Gemara that speaks about the importance about speaking
to Rivka's point about the the standard hierarchy in the גמרא Gemara
about תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, that a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham should
marry a בת תלמיד חכם, bat talmid chacham, you know, not imagining
yet the woman herself is a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but at
least she's a בת תלמיד חכם, bat talmid chacham, you know, for
the genes, to have the multiplier effect on יחוס, yichus, but
the
יחוס yichus in, I mean the גמרא... Gemara...
It occurred to me the there's no reference I've seen in any
of the rabbinic literature to the Jews of Ethiopia until the late
ראשונים. Rishonim. Correct. So they may not have had any concept that
there were huge groups of Jews with really all of whom had
dark skin.
Wait a minute, the Jews you were talking about before, they attribute
them that they say they go back as far as far back
as the time of the גמרא? Gemara?
No, no, I'm saying that the people who wrote the גמרא Gemara
would have never seen anyone.
I don't know if they even existed, the Ethiopian Jews so far.
Whether they were Jews, they were there
before the גמרא, Gemara, but that doesn't mean they didn't
wait, the Ethiopian Jews say they come from, you know, a relationship,
whatever, with שלמה, Shlomo, or whatever, but I don't think scholars believe
that at all.
Right, and so
our thing is that the גמרא Gemara didn't see them. They have
no knowledge that they existed.
We don't even know if there's any הלכה. Halacha. There's no reference
in our literature.
These words here refer to don't refer to Rashi uses the word
כושי Kushi to refer to a color of skin. It does not
refer to an actual, you know, race. I think that's correct.
And this last paragraph actually supports that.
Correct, correct. It's talking about a characteristic, it's not talking about a
race.
You know, it's ironic because within the group that's everything's okay, we're
supposed to marry each other. Right. But then you get a dwarf
who's not supposed to marry a dwarf, but who's he going to
feel comfortable with? A tall person? Or a tall person marrying tiny
person? Not so comfortable.
Right, right. And pituitary dwarfism is not this is not a law
what's being said here. It's sort of being put down here as
advice, okay? Nobody translated this as
הלכה. Halacha. What did you say, Charlie, that pituitary gland dwarfism is
not genetic?
If two dwarfs marry each other, they'll have normal sized children.
All right. All right. Moving on. החרש ושוטה ושיכור. Hecheresh veshoteh veshikor.
Or שיכור, shikor, the גמרא Gemara says drunk, מחלל
עבודה. mechalel avodah. That desecrates the עבודה, avodah, which is noteworthy meaning
two points. Number one is it's not based on a moment, it's
based on a separate problem. And number two, we've been saying that
our entire list is not מומים, mumim, is this category called שוה
בזרעו של אהרן, shaveh bezaro shel Aharon, and we said that the
distinctive aspect of that besides not being a prohibition, but being a
positive מצוה, mitzvah, is that the עבודה avodah is not invalidated. But
somebody who's drunk does invalidate the עבודה. avodah. The Torah says,
יין ושכר אל תשת אתה ובניך אתך בבאכם אל אהל מועד ולא
תמותו ולהבדיל בין הקדש ובין החל, Yayin veshichar al tesht atah uvanecha
itach bevochem el ohel moed velo tamutu ulehavdil bein hakodesh uvein hachol,
to distinguish between holy and profane, from which we learn that by
being drunk you lose that distinction and you profane the עבודה. avodah.
Doesn't sound like genetic either, the החרש. Hecheresh. I know.
No, no, we're moving on from genetics now. החרש והשוטה ושיכור, Hecheresh
vehashoteh veshikor, whatever, nobody said any of this had to be genetic.
These are just some problem. Nobody has identified that these problems are
only issues if they're genetic. Is alcoholism an issue? All right, that's
fine. That's definitely a question. That's not we're not talking about that
issue, okay? So,
the גמרא Gemara says, בהדי מומי דמחללי עבודה איבעי למיחשביה. behadei mumi
demachli avodah ibei lemichshavei. It should be counted with the מומים mumim
that,
you know, invalidate the
עבודה, avodah, that profane the עבודה. avodah. So the גמרא Gemara says,
בשאר דברים משכרים. beshar dvarim mashker. No, we're talking about non-wine. We're
talking about other things that cause drunkenness, alcohol which isn't wine, and
we're assuming that the biblical prohibition of being drunk, although it says
יין ושכר, yayin veshichar, so the question is how do you define
ושכר? veshichar? Okay, is ושכר veshichar like particularly high-alcohol wine? Is it
other types of things? So this is debated about what is included
in that prohibition and what
profanes the עבודה. avodah. So we're talking about things that are not
in the biblical prohibition of יין ושכר, yayin veshichar, but are a
problem because they through your actions, you know, they make you stand
out from other כהנים kohanim and therefore it's... no, not rabbinic, it
could be the biblical of שוה בזרעו של אהרן. shaveh bezaro shel
Aharon. That's not exactly clear. Is that category of שוה בזרעו של
אהרן... shaveh bezaro shel Aharon... I mean it could be, we know
about other temporary things, about a מום mum over there. So if
we are saying that certain types of things, even if they're not
physical, but you know are visibly clear that you are... make you
stand out and different, like asthmatic and epileptic and so on, that
seems to be the same point here about the deaf-mute and the
drunk. So I'm not sure it's rabbinic. Okay, it is an interesting
point that it's something that is very temporary. Okay, but you know,
we do have also temporary מומים, mumim, but it's not מחללי עבודה.
mechaleli avodah. What?
Rav understands שכר shichar as יין דרך שכרותו. yayin derech shikruto.
There you go. Right, exactly. Alcoholic wine as a highly alcoholic... but
is debated in the משנה, Mishnah, and לא כרבי יהודה. lo k'Rabbi
Yehuda. דתניא, detanya, as we taught, not like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
because אכל דבילה קעילית ושתה חלב או דבש, achal deveilah kilit veshata
chalav o devash,
like the חנוכה Chanukah story, right? Was it the חנוכה Chanukah story
was the חלב? chalav? No, that was יעל Yael was also they
have right, they have they're there too. Okay, anyway, so anyway, these
types of things which the גמרא Gemara understood cause a certain type
degree of inebriation...
issue of all of it or any?
No, any of these. Certain types of dates or honey or or
milk. It's funny it doesn't just mention like beer, or anyway.
Anyway והנכנס למקדש חייב ve-ha-nichnas la-mikdash chayav you transgress. That's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, but we don't rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, or this is not going like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so
it's not in the תורה's Torah category of יין ושכר, yayin ve-shechar,
but it is a separate problem here about a type of a
מום mum or not a מום, mum, but שוה בזרעו של אהרן.
shaveh be-zar'o shel Aharon. קטן Katan is not a problem.
קטן Katan is
not a problem and wait but Rashi
here, yeah, Rashi says mead. Mead.
Oh that's a good point, I forgot that, right. Rashi says the
honey is not honey straight, but it is right mead. It is
right, it is liquor. Okay. All right, so now that's that, that's
we are not going to get done today. That
that is all of these things which are again not מומים mumim
at least the way the גמרא Gemara conceptualizes it, but this category
of שוה בזרעו של אהרן, shaveh be-zar'o shel Aharon, the next sort
of the the center of the bell-shaped curve of כהנים. Kohanim. And
again the fascinating thing is is that they go beyond just physical
aspects. They have things like as we said epilepsy, drunk, שוטה, shoteh,
חרש, cheresh, things that are not just even physical but maybe are
to some degree visible. And the question with all of these is
which of them are significant and which are trivial enough to be
ignored and we never had a good way to quantify that. Not
everything that's physical and visible is counted.
Now we have one final משנה Mishnah that gives us a little
bit of the reverse. אלו כשרים באדם ופסולים בבהמה. Elu kesherim ba-adam
u-pesulim be-behemah.
The following list, we've mentioned an entire פרק perek of things that
are not a problem by animals, but are a problem by humans.
Here's a list that's not a problem by human כהנים, Kohanim, but
is a problem by animals. אותו ואת בנו, Oto ve-et beno, you
can't bring an animal and its child as a קרבן korban on
the same day. You can't even שחט shacht an animal and and
its child on the same day. But nobody's שחטינג shachting כהנים Kohanim
and their children, it's a funny comparison, but the presumably hope not,
but the comparison is is about a כהן Kohen and his son,
for example,
serving, serving at the same time and that seems to be the
analogy.
טרפה, Treifah, that's very interesting, an internal injury, a טרפה. treifah. So
we've said not a מום, mum, it's completely internal. Okay, although I
I want to remind you that the גמרא Gemara before discussed the
question about whether if an animal has an extra or missing organ,
not just a טרפה treifah hole but a missing organ internally, is
that a problem of not being תמים? tamim? The גמרא Gemara seemed
to rule that it was and how would you know if that
were true by a כהן, Kohen, I don't know, but that's an
interesting question to ask if it's not just a טרפה treifah problem
but a complete extra or missing organ, right what would be the
story there? But anyway טרפה treifah is not a problem by
humans. ויוצא דופן, Ve-yotzei dofen, a cesarean section, because based on the
verse
about שור או כשב או עז כי יולד shor o chesev o
ez ki yivaled if it's born which means natural birth is a
requirement for קרבנות korbanot not for כהנים. Kohanim. And now some have
this line some don't.
ושנעבדה בהם עבירה ושמיתת אדם, Ve-sheneevdah bahem aveirah ve-she-mitat adam, things that
were used in bestiality or that were used in
that an animal that gored, right a שור הנסקל. shor ha-niskal. So
those are types of things that we learned before from verses are
invalid as קרבנות korbanot but not for כהנים. Kohanim. And and it's
interesting that that line is taken out because
because we do have an issue if you know a כהן Kohen
in terms of if they've sinned. So they actually can continue to
serve. We're going to talk at the end of the משנה Mishnah
about one or two particular כהן Kohen related sins that are a
rabbinic problem at least not a biblical one. The issues the two
issues that get raised are number one if they worshipped עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah even if they've done תשובה teshuvah that completely invalidates them
for obvious reasons, labels them you know as priests of another religion.
And the other issue question is ושמיתת אדם, ve-she-mitat adam, that's interesting,
murder. Because the גמרא Gemara does say that if a כהן Kohen
commits murder he cannot even if he's done תשובה teshuvah and maybe
even if it was completely accidental. There are some very poignant cases
about that. Anyway questions about those cases about תשובה teshuvah and accident
whether those are included, right that would be killing but would it
be murder, right anyway. So that's a question whether that's included but
that's learned from a verse in terms of דוכנינג duchening from the
verse of ידיכם דמים מלאו, yedeichem damim maleu, your hands are filled
with blood. How can you raise up your hands to bless? A
particular focus on the hands and the sort of the metaphor if
you would of bloody hands. It is not brought down explicitly by
the עבודה, avodah, by other things, which is interesting and surprising. Okay
so that's an interesting question. But those are the areas in which
are raised for כהנים. Kohanim.
ושנעבדה בהם עבירה Ve-sheneevdah bahem aveirah means engaged in bestiality, a sexual
sin. Homosexuality? Well, the
גמרא Gemara questions if that line is even there. If it were
being applied to כהנים Kohanim or compared to כהנים Kohanim then the
issue would be whatever sexual sins we could be talking about. Okay.
So that's okay, it would not invalidate
them, yes. Okay. והנושא נשים בעבירה. Ve-ha-nosei nashim be-aveirah. Now here is
the one עבירה aveirah that is an issue for כהנים Kohanim in
terms of serving if they violate the כהנים Kohanim laws in their
sin and they are sort of still in that state meaning that
they have married against the כהנים Kohanim laws, married a גרושה gerushah
for example, and that's still their current state so that we cannot
tolerate them to function as כהנים Kohanim when they are in that
state of flouting you know the laws of כהנים. Kohanim. Okay so
פסול עד שידיר הנאה pasul ad she-yadir hana'ah but the way you
can address it is before even being divorced. is that he takes
a vow that makes this woman forbidden to him sexually and therefore
he's going to have to divorce her. So therefore until he gets
around to doing the divorce, that at least sort of addresses that
problem and allows him to do the
עבודה. avoda. ומהמטמא למתים vehametamei lemetim now what's the other big restriction
of כהנים cohanim in addition to who they can marry is becoming
is coming טמא tamei contact with the dead. Now there, okay, let's
say a כהן cohen regularly flouts that law. He regularly I don't
know in his side job he works in a he works in
a cemetery. He he tends a cemetery. He regularly flouts that. Okay,
will he be able to do the עבודה? avoda? Now there's a
somewhat of a difference, which is that at the moment he's doing
the עבודה avoda he's not in violation of a particular law, right?
If he became טהור tahor before he did the עבודה avoda as
opposed to the one who's married against the laws of the כהנים.
cohanim. So but nevertheless let's see what the פסול pasul that he's
also
invalid עד שיקבל עליו שלא יהא מטמא למתים ad sheyekabel alav shelo
yehei metamei lemetim until he takes an you know obligates himself, makes
a commitment not to continue doing it in the future. So the
גמרא gemara is going to discuss why in one case you needed
a vow and in the other case you needed a commitment.
What do you mean taking a commitment? He's committed from birth.
Yes, but clearly he himself has not has you know has violated
that. So you know so he needs to accept it as a
personal responsibility, acknowledge what his responsibility is. Yes.
Does the OU have a policy that כהנים cohanim that rabbis performing
the weddings for כהן cohen and a גרושה? gerusha?
I mean not a specific policy different than any policy about following
הלכה. halacha. No, I mean it's you know like anything about doing
following הלכה, halacha, you know.
So if one of your מסמכים musmachim would do that, they would
not be?
I think absolutely not, yes. Do you have something you need to
share with me?
I'm just asking about the OU כהן cohen and divorcee, you would
consider that?
I mean obviously when those cases come up, you know, פוסקים poskim
try to find in any particular case either you know or you
know whether there are you know the basic way that that that
is handled is either that if it's possible he's not a כהן
cohen or maybe she's not a גרושה, gerusha, maybe the original קידושין
kiddushin wasn't good and so on. But if you cannot find a
you know particular you know circumstances in those cases, you're not allowed
to violate פסק.
psak. What? You're not allowed to violate הלכה.
halacha. Go figure. You're not allowed to violate הלכה, halacha, correct. All
right. Exactly. So let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. ואלו
כשרין באדם ve'elu kesherin ba'adam
and the following are okay. Okay so now we're going to look
at this משנה. mishna. מאי אותו ואת בנו? mai oto ve'et beno?
What is the אותו ואת בנו oto ve'et beno example that we
can even be talking about to compare to the case of קרבנות?
korbanot? אילימא אהרן ובניו, eileima aharon uvanav,
if we mean that the כהן cohen and his sons can serve
in the בית המקדש beit hamikdash on the same day let's say,
דכוותיה תייש ובנו dechavateih tayish uveno so the question is bringing a
ram and the child as a קרבן, korban, מנא לן mena lan
that אותו ואת בנו oto ve'et beno
is not about males? והתניא vehatanya אותו ואת בנו נוהג בנקבות ואינו
נוהג בזכרים oto ve'et beno noheig binekeivot ve'eino noheig bizcharim by at
least the mother, the the parent has to be the mother
and not by males, not by fathers. אלא תיישה ובנה. ela tayisha
uvenah. Okay so we're talking about a female goat and the child.
דכוותיה הכא כהנת ובנה. dechavateih hacha kohenet uvenah. So the comparison would
be כהנת ובנה, kohenet uvenah, a female כהן cohen and her child.
It's interesting that at times the גמרא gemara calls a כהנת kohenet
as opposed to בת כהן. bat kohen. We discussed that when we
did the end of חולין. chullin. Anyway, כהנת בת עבודה היא? kohenet
bat avoda hi? You think that a female כהן cohen can do
the עבודה? avoda? How is it an irrelevant discussion? So לעולם אהרן
ובניו. le'olam aharon uvanav.
Fine, we're talking about a male כהן cohen and his son. דכוותיה
הכא תייש ובנו. dechavateih hacha tayish uveno. So fine, a ram and
or whatever a goat, excuse me, and the child. ובאמי באמר רבא
uve'amei be'amar rava and they say in ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael משמיה
דרבי יוסי בר אבין mishmeih derabbi yosei bar avin אדא אמרה ada
amrah this tells you אדא אמרה ada amrah is an interesting sort
of idiom אדא ada like this, it's a funny word, it doesn't
I think appear by itself. Anyway, אדא אמרה ada amrah this tells
you חנניה היא chananya hi or משנת חנניה mishnat chananya דתניא detanya
which we taught in a ברייתא braita אותו ואת בנו נוהג בנקבות
ואינו נוהג בזכרים oto ve'et beno noheig binekeivot ve'eino noheig bizcharim applies
by females not males, at least the parent. חנניה אומר נוהג בזכרים
ובנקבות chananya omer noheig bizcharim uvinekeivot even if the parent is male.
So according to חנניה chananya that it applies by male parents, there's
no comparable issue that applies to
כהנים. cohanim. Okay. והנושא נשים בעבירה vehanosei nashim ba'aveira a כהן cohen
that is married in violation, he's transgressing the sin of marrying a
גרושה gerusha or אלמנה. almana. תנא. tana. Not אלמנה, almana, excuse me,
that's כהן גדול, kohen gadol, a גרושה gerusha or
חלוצה chalutza whatever. תנא. tana. נודר ועובד noder ve'oved he takes a
vow and can continue doing the עבודה, avoda, he doesn't have to
stop and leave the בית המקדש beit hamikdash I guess if it's
found out. Like how did it happen that oh my god they
just realized I was married to a גרושה? gerusha? Somehow they found
out about it and he was in the middle of the עבודה.
avoda. He doesn't have to stop and leave and do the גירושין
geirushin right now, he can take a נדר neder now and יורד
ומגרש yoreid umegaresh when he gets down from the from the altar
then he divorces his wife. So the גמרא gemara says וליחוש דלמא
אזיל לגבי חכם ושרי ליה veleichush dilma azil legabei chacham vesharei leih
why is a נדר neder enough? Maybe he'll go to a חכם
chacham and he'll get a היתר heter on his נדר. neder. Now
that's interesting that we would think that a חכם chacham would even
agree to that because I mean it's a נדר, neder, you know,
what type of an argument could you give why the vow shouldn't
be binding if you're in violation of the law? What?
He's annulling a vow.
And he's מושבע ועומד מהר סיני.
mushba v'omed m'Har Sinai.
Well, that's the difference between נדר neder and a שבועה. shavuah. That's
the question. מושבע ועומד מהר סיני, mushba v'omed m'Har Sinai, that a
vow doesn't take effect on top of an already pre-existing biblical obligation,
is about like is when you're making a שבועה. shavuah. A שבועה
shavuah relates to your personal responsibility. Okay, this is a נדר. neder.
A נדר neder is object-oriented. So therefore it says that the woman
that she is forbidden to him without directly relating to his personal
responsibility. The גמרא Gemara for example says if somebody takes מושבע ועומד
mushba v'omed is usually used in the reverse when you're trying to
counteract your biblical obligation. If somebody takes a שבועה shavuah like I
will never wear תפילין tefillin or I'll never sit in a סוכה,
sukkah, then that doesn't work because you have a pre-existing שבועה shavuah
obligation, you know, that you're trying to counteract. If however you say
all the סוכות sukkot in the world are אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah
to me, you're not directly countering your obligation, you are just creating
them as forbidden objects and now indirectly it's impossible for you to
fulfill it. So that's exactly what's going on here. But here it's
reinforcing your biblical obligation, not counteracting it. The question is why a
חכם, chacham, you know, will allow it. But whatever, either way we're
still concerned that that's a possibility. So but that's exactly what the
גמרא Gemara addresses in the next line. One second. קסבר צריך לפרט
את הנדר. kasavar tzarich lepharet et haneder. No, you because we are
assuming that you have to enunciate, you have to tell the חכם,
chacham, you don't just say oh I made a vow and then
I realized certain things I never would have taken. We say you
have to be specific and since you have to be specific, no
חכם chacham worth his, you know, salt is going to allow it
if he knows specifically that you are that by being מתיר הנדר
matir haneder it's allowing you to continue to do a sin. Yes
Bobby.
So so a man is illegally married a woman and has six
kids with her. Right. And now he decides he gets off
the, I no longer married. So goodbye kids.
Okay, so that raises a good question which is is that why
oh absolutely, you know, nobody halachically can sanction the
violation and clearly you're in violation of biblical law, you know, and
a בית דין Beit Din obviously, you know, no halachic rabbi is
going to marry a כהן Kohen in violation of these things. But
the רמא Rama does say
that nowadays we do not, the גמרא Gemara in כתובות Ketubot or
whatever other cases discusses compelling divorce, you know, whether people are when
people are in violation, whether it's a כהן Kohen who's married to
a woman he's not allowed to, somebody who's married to let's say
I don't know a ממזר, mamzer, ממזרת, mamzeret, or cases about let's
say I don't know where the גמרא Gemara says that if you
don't have kids in ten years you have to get divorced or
you can remarry and have kids. And the רמא Rama basically says
nowadays we don't force divorces. You know, so we just, you know,
even though the גמרא Gemara talks about compelling these things we don't
now. While that's true we don't force divorces, nobody's going to say
that
as an application of this למעשה l'ma'aseh is that if a כהן
Kohen is married to a גרושה gerushah he's not allowed to דוכן
duchen in the שול. shul. And nobody says oh we're going to
remove that restriction. Clearly we cannot sort of condone and allow the
person to function as a כהן Kohen while he's in violations of
the laws of כהונה. kehunah. Okay, but in the sense that we're
going to actively compel as opposed to just not sort of, you
know, condone it by allowing this type of thing, that we don't
do nowadays. But the גמרא Gemara does imagine that we would. The
גמרא Gemara does imagine that yes, we would compel divorces even though
it would, even though it would destroy the family unit or
law breaking in general.
Right, although the גמרא Gemara if you ask the גמרא Gemara what's
the ideal, the גמרא Gemara would say the ideal is to stop
the violation and to, right.
It's not clear from the text whether this is just violating the
כהונה kehunah laws or maybe marrying someone whom any Jew is prohibited
from.
Right. So it seems but it is clear from context it does
seem very much that this is because if he's flouting כהונה kehunah
laws he cannot continue to serve as a כהן. Kohen. Okay, now
it is an interesting point, like let's say you have somebody that
is basically I don't know, he doesn't flout כהונה kehunah laws but
he's a complete non-believer, he regularly eats pork, he regularly does all
these types of things, right? Now the גמרא Gemara before has discussed
issues about כהנים kohanim that accept all the laws of כהונה. kehunah.
Fine, he's kept all the laws of כהונה kehunah but he flouts
everything else, everything else, right? Does that does that be like a
מומר mumar and a מין min and all these other categories but
as a כהן Kohen he's a good כהן, Kohen, right? Would that
actually invalidate him? It's a very good question. I'd have to, you
know.
That's sort of what I was saying, like let's say you know
you're a really miserable person and you lie and you steal and
all that.
Yeah, right, but so yeah I don't know, I'd have to think
if we have if there's, it's not occurring to me offhand if
we've got, I mean that's basically the category of like מין min
and מומר, mumar, somebody that's a consistent violator just doesn't happen to
be in the כהן Kohen category. I mean there is a גמרא
Gemara about giving like מתנת כהונה matnat kehunah to the כהנים kohanim
that are that are observant. Right, but that's about giving but that's
not invalidating them, preferable. Right, yeah, I'd have to, giving an
עליה aliyah at every time
as כהן.
Kohen. That's another thing that we don't do, that's correct, we don't
give them an עליה aliyah as כהן Kohen because that acknowledges their
כהן Kohen role and status. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
הני למאן דאמר צריך לפרט הנדר. hani liman de'amar tzarich lifaret haneder.
That's fine if you say you have to enunciate the specifics, right,
when we say by היתר נדרים, heter nedarim, we say at the
end of היתר נדרים heter nedarim what we do in generic היתר
נדרים heter nedarim at ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah we say אף על
פי... af al pi...
אי אפשר לפרטם כראוי.
ee
efshar lefortam k'ra'uy. Exactly,
exactly. We sort of say that language which is I can't enunciate
them, there's too many, consider it as if I've enunciated them. Anyway,
the גמרא's Gemara not considering that possibility or else it wouldn't have
had an answer. But the גמרא Gemara says how about the person
that says למאן דאמר אין צריך לפרט את הנדר, liman de'amar ein
tzarich lifaret et haneder, maybe you'll get away with a היתר חכם,
heter chacham, מאי איכא למימר, mai ikka lemeimar, what can you say?
So the גמרא Gemara says דאדרינן ליה ברבים. de'adrinan lei berabbim.
No, you take a vow in public and public vow presumably because
it becomes objectified and it's not just my subjective thoughts when I
was vowing it but it's now property of the masses, it's a
public matter, so I am not in a position to say oh
had I been thinking this I would not have done it right
because it's no longer just about what I was thinking. It's sort
of it's out there, it's objective and therefore I can no longer
do a היתר נדר heter neder if it's done in public. So
we're not up to that yet. So the גמרא Gemara says הדי
הכא למאן דאמר נדר שהודר ברבים אין לו הפרה. hadi hacha liman
de'amar neder shehudu berabbim ein lo hafara. That's good according to that
opinion that if it's in public you don't have התרה. hatara. אלא
למאן דאמר יש לו הפרה תהא התרה מאי איכא למימר. ella liman
de'amar yesh lo hafara tehi hatara mai ikka lemeimar. What if it's
done in what about the opinion that even in public you can
מתיר matir it? How do we solve the problem? So the גמרא
Gemara says דאדרינן ליה על דעתא דרבים. de'adrinan lei al da'ata derabbim.
You do it not just in public or not in public but
you do it on the according to the mindset of the masses.
You do it you know so which is meaning my vow should
be defined based on sort of not what I'm thinking but you
explicitly say based on how the masses would interpret it and understand
it, on their דעת da'at not on my דעת. da'at. So it's
not just that you've in in the act of doing it have
made it public but you explicitly say it's based on their mindset.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר מימר, amar Meimar, and מימר Meimar
says הלכתא, hilchata, the הלכה halacha is, אפילו למאן דאמר נדר שהודר
ברבים יש לו הפרה שתהא התרה, afilu liman de'amar neder shehudu berabbim
yesh lo hafara shetehi hatara, even
for the ones that says that if it's in public you can
מתיר matir it, על דעת רבים אין לו הפרה. al da'at rabbim
ein lo hafara. But if it's on their דעת da'at you cannot.
So therefore that's how you solve the problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says but by the way parenthetically you should be aware והני מילי
לדבר רשות. vehani mili lidvar reshut. When can you not be מתיר
matir something that's done על דעת רבים? al da'at rabbim? You can't
do it when it's for the sake of a matter of discretion.
אבל לדבר מצוה, aval lidvar mitzvah, if it's important to מתיר matir
the נדר neder for the sake of being able to do a
מצוה, mitzvah, יש לו הפרה yesh lo hafara you can do it
even when it's done על דעת רבים. al da'at rabbim. What's the
example? כי ההוא, ki hahu, right, דמקרי דרדקי. de'mikri dardeki. So as
if there weren't enough things to be upset about yet, there's a
person that was a that was a teacher of of children like
a kindergarten teacher, that's what דמקרי דרדקי de'mikri dardeki is. אדריה רב
אחא דקפש בינוקי. adarei Rav Acha dekapsha beyanukei.
So רב אחא Rav Acha made a נדר neder that nobody that
he could not be people could not derive benefit learn from him,
question about how he made the נדר neder and it affected other
people, but whatever it was because he was he was misusing the
kids. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, מלקי אותן ומיתים. malke otan
umesim. Not just corporal punishment but they actually died. Corporal punishment was
accepted as a given, okay, but actually overly I don't know if
you have to go so far to say they died but he
was a little bit too strict in his corporal punishment. So he
made a vow presumably על דעת רבים al da'at rabbim that he
could no longer teach, that he was forbidden to derive benefit teaching
benefit from him and ואהדריה רבינא. hahdrei Ravina. And רבינא Ravina reversed
it and basically was מתיר matir the נדר. neder. How could he
be מתיר matir the נדר? neder? It was על דעת רבים al
da'at rabbim is the assumption. דאשתכח דהוה דייק כוותיה. de'ishkach de'havei dayka
kevatei. There was you could there was no other teachers that were
as good as him. He was such a great teacher. So which
is obviously very very troubling and we can shake our heads but
we all know that this is exactly the reason why abuse happens
so often is because the person oh but I mean he's such
a good רבי rabbi he's such a good this and that and
that and it's reasons that you dismiss the rumors or the knowledge
of problems because of everything else that you know if if the
person was was was you know was not doing good other you
know good in his job then you'd be more ready to find
you know to the charges of the abuse. So obviously you know
I don't think you have to go as far as רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi says he actually kids would die as a result would
die as a result that's obviously particularly particularly you know a real
problem but even if it's just that he was using too much
force you know even in a society that had corporal you know
that used it that would hit kids but it was perceived of
that that was overboard you know this is obviously very disturbing that
that was sort of that that was ignored you know put aside
because of what a good teacher he was. Anyway so that is
that is right issues about על דעת רבים al da'at rabbim what
they fired by one school and he
gets hired by another exactly now right one school gets rid of
him the other school hires him it's exactly what happens in cases
of abuse.
And here he was still able to
reverse רב אחא Rav Acha also.
Yeah well it's a whole question also maybe רב אחא Rav Acha
himself went for a התרה hatara it's also a question how could
you make a נדר neder what was the case exactly anyway for
if we could bracket that very disturbing human reality if you want
to just talk about for a minute the logic of this the
על דעת... al da'at... And ברבים *be'rabbim* תוספות *Tosafos* points out that
it could be the reason why על דעת רבים *al da'as rabbim*
has a התרה *hatara* is since you're saying I'm doing it on
their on the intent of the masses so then that would be
well most people would want would not want a נדר *neder* to
apply if it was getting in the way of a מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah*. So that's why for the sake of a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*
again ignoring the very disturbing application here it would be you would
be able to have a התרה *hatara* and that's a difference between
the logic of על דעת רבים *al da'as rabbim* and ברבים *be'rabbim*.
That ברבים *be'rabbim* just objectifies it takes it out of the question
about what anybody is thinking. You said the נדר *neder* that's the
way it is it's just its objective definition you can't make any
you know implicit limitations based on what you or others would be
thinking. על דעת רבים *al da'as rabbim* still has it based on
what people would have thought just not what you would have thought
but what anybody would have thought but that might still have certain
limitations like the case here about the what do you call it
about when it's for the sake of a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. But
again very disturbing that that's considered to be you know a מצוה
*mitzvah* that counteracts you know that that's the type of trade-off that
is being made here and as we know that this is just
so common in cases of abuse these types of implicit trade-offs are
being made. Yes.
Do you think this story is included here as a warning? What?
Do you think this story is included here as a warning?
As a warning in what way?
In other words why would they have included that story?
Because whenever the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discusses because this is like this
is a this is like a paragraph that gets repeated a couple
of times in ש"ס *Shas*. When they discuss the issue of על
דעת רבים *al da'as rabbim* and ברבים *be'rabbim* and then they give
this example so this is like this is not the only place
it occurs it's like regularly thrown in when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
discussing this topic. This was like seen as a good example of
this idea that it doesn't apply במקום מצוה *bemakom mitzvah*. But again
going to Rivka's point how disturbing is this is that in terms
of being internalized this as an appropriate type of a trade-off that's
you know that's being made is you know is deeply disturbing. Yes.
I think we can be glad that this מסכת *masechet* is rarely
studied.
Right well for this.
All right very very quick question. Yes. But if he was let's
say
stealing right then you wouldn't be doing that right because that's actually
because you're allowed to do corporal punishment in the eyes of the
גמרא *Gemara* but you're not allowed to steal.
Well but according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* which makes it obviously obviously
like you know just impossible to contemplate that it was to the
point that they died you know you're not allowed to kill I
mean it just doesn't matter you know and to do it to
that degree right even within the גמרא *Gemara* they accepted that as
acceptable within the education not to that degree and how could you
tolerate that end result? Right how could you tolerate that your kid
might die as a result? So
I I I still very profoundly difficult.
Let's move to a closer than the women of the... Well that's
what I'm saying.
No no no that's what I'm trying to get to. Even if
he was since since corporal punishment is allowed to begin with it's
okay but if he was doing something that wasn't allowed to be
doing to begin with then it wouldn't have been okay. You know
that's not a מצוה *mitzvah* right?
Yes I don't know the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that it was something
that wasn't allowed to be doing that's why he was hooted in
the first place. I mean it raises sort of you know Bobby's
question implicitly would have said right why don't we say same you
know what I to reframe your question Bobby I want to say
well you know to have the husband leave his his his wife
and six kids what about the מצוה *mitzvah* of raising the kids?
What about the fact about you know what about their you know
their upbringing and all those other values? Why are those getting thrown
out of the out of the windows? Feeding them. Right exactly. So
but I'm just saying that implicitly what your question is is that
here you're ignoring the problem of hitting for the sake of being
a good school teacher right and we don't why don't we make
you know the trade-off about you know about the מתיר *matir* his
נדר *neder* in terms of divorcing his wife for the sake of
raising the kids? Right so yeah I mean anyway we let's not
say
it out loud but what we're really talking about is sexual abuse.
I mean that is really it's being...
Right well that's not what's being discussed here but that is what
occurs right that's what I was that's what I was referring to
that cases about abuse is much more than just physical abuse. Right.
All right. ומתמי למסין *Ve'matmi le'mesin*. All right. מאי שנא הכא דסגי
ליה בקבלה
*Mai shna hacha desagi lei bekabala* no no no stop a minute.
So are we looking at some of these תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim*
who look at this stuff and figure these guys got away with
it in those days so why can't I?
What?
I've never seen that.
No I mean look the people that actually do the abuse have
real pathological problems. I you know it is I would be shocked
if anybody sort of felt oh I have license because I see
that in this גמרא *Gemara* he got away with beating the kids
that allows me to sexually abuse the kids. I mean these are
talking about deep you know psychological pathological issues. The bigger question I
think is not the people doing it but the way the community
is responds to it and that you know that is where a
גמרא *Gemara* like this can be you know very dangerous and I
agree it's a real issue. All right. ומתמי למסין *Ve'matmi le'mesin*. מאי
שנא הכא דסגי ליה בקבלה *Mai shna hacha desagi lei bekabala* why
in the case of the person that becomes a כהן kohen. *kohen*
becomes טמא *tamei* is making a commitment good enough ומאי שנא התם
דמטרינן ליה *u'mai shna hasam de'matrinan lei* and why by the case
about married the wives you need a נדר *neder*? So the גמרא
*Gemara* says which is obviously taking it to another step. The גמרא
*Gemara* says התם יצרא תקיף ליה *hatam yitzra takif lei* there his
he has a stronger יצר הרע yetzer hara *yetzer hara* now. It
could be a יצר הרע for sex, but it could also be
יצר הרע because it's his wife and kids. You know, and who
wants to, you know, and that to to leave wife and kids
and to leave a marriage is very different than to I don't
know leave your job as being a as being you know as
working in a cemetery or whatever is motivating you to be מטמא
למתים. metamei lemesim. I would also add like I said before that
the case of the married is a present issue even in the
moment he's doing the עבודה. avodah. He's still in sin. Whereas the
case of מטמא למתים metamei lemesim is only a regular habit but
not a present issue when he is doing the עבודה. avodah. Okay
okay well that's true but then קבלה kabala would be enough for
that. הדרן עלך מומין אלו. hadran alach mumin elu. So that was
a very very challenging פרק. perek. And now we move on and
maybe we'll get I don't know well let's yes let's do the
משנה mishnah exactly where we talk where we get to actually this
of all the stuff of בכור bechor that is learned it is
this פרק perek because this פרק perek talks about the concept of
בכור. bechor. Not about animals but about humans not about מומין mumin
but about the status of a בכור bechor for two הלכות: halachos:
פדיון הבן pidyon haben and for בכור bechor of getting פי שנים
pi shenayim getting double. And we have a nice opening משנה mishnah
that compares the different definitions of the בכור bechor for those two
categories. So let's take a look.
יש בכור לנחלה ואינו בכור לכהן בכור לכהן ואינו בכור לנחלה. yesh
bechor lenachalah veino bechor lekohen bechor lekohen veino bechor lenachalah. Sometimes somebody
is considered a בכור bechor for inheritance for getting a double portion
but not for כהן. kohen Sometimes for כהן kohen and not for
inheritance. בכור לנחלה ולכהן. bechor lenachalah ulekohen. Somebody is considered a בכור
bechor for both purposes. Obviously that's easy just a normal בכור. bechor.
ויש שאינו בכור לא לנחלה ולא לכהן. veyesh sheino bechor lo lenachalah
velo lekohen. And there's some that are not don't count for either.
Now חז"ל chazal tell you the conceptual difference and then we'll look
at the application. The conceptual difference for both you have to be
a male firstborn but the difference is is that by the פדיון
הבן pidyon haben it says פטר רחם peter rechem the breaching of
the womb. So the first difference is that that's defined by the
firstborn of the mother. You could have multiple one father multiple mothers
you know multiple wives and every firstborn male of the of the
from the woman's perspective is פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. The בכור bechor
for inheritance is the firstborn of the father. So that's one major
difference. The other major difference is is that by the by the
כהן kohen? it's referred to as פטר רחם peter rechem and by
the father of inheritance it's referred to as ראשית אונו reishis ono
the first of his strength. And the way the גמרא conceptualizes the
difference is that ראשית אונו reishis ono means that it has to
have been a viable child. So if you have a miscarriage first
and then a child so for פדיון הבן pidyon haben that is
not פטר רחם. peter rechem. It is not the first one out
of the womb.
Whereas for no the the viable
one the second one that was viable
or even a miscarriage count or stillborn?
No even miscarriage. After the child's been already like forty days and
is formed the next child is not פדיון הבן pidyon haben but
for a for בכור bechor for פי שנים pi shenayim it is
because it's the first viable child. So as long as it's the
first viable child is male that gets the פי שנים. pi shenayim.
Okay that's very interesting. And cesarean is right well we'll talk about
cesarean. Okay so let's take a look at the גמרא at the
rest of the משנה. mishnah. Okay הבא אחר
נפלים. haba acher nefalim.
Somebody that comes after miscarriages. בכור לנחלה. bechor lenachalah. Thank you. איזהו
בכור לנחלה ואינו בכור לכהן? eizehu bechor lenachalah veino bechor lekohen? Which
is the case of firstborn for inheritance but not for כהן? Kohen
So it's going to focus on what I said that it has
to be
for a לנחלה lenachalah it has to be the first viable child
but for a לכהן lekohen it has to be the first regardless
of viability. So הבא אחר נפלים. haba acher nefalim. One who comes
after a miscarriage. אף על פי שיצא ראשו חי. af al pi
sheyatza rosho chai. So even if the first child you know emerged
alive but nevertheless the way רש"י says it was an eight-month-old child
it was not fully it was not fully developed so it was
going to die. So so the fact that it wasn't viable even
if it emerged initially alive so non-viable birth. ובן תשעה שיצא ראשו
מת. uven tishah sheyatza rosho meis. Or fully developed one that came
out dead. So it actually either was not viable or actually it
was not even alive. Okay so if the first child was not
viable or not alive the second one will not be פטר רחם
peter rechem will not be the בכור bechor for the פדיון הבן
pidyon haben because it's not the first child but it will be
the firstborn for inheritance because it's the first viable child. Okay so
that's one case. המפלת כמין בהמה חיה ועוף. hamapeles kemin behemah chayah
vaof. Or just a simple case of miscarriage as like domestic animals
wild animals and birds. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. Let's say
the miscarriage looks like of the first child looks like not human
it looks like animals or birds so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
that's still considered a miscarriage it's still a human fetus there just
misshapen and therefore the second child is again not a בכור bechor
for פדיון הבן pidyon haben but is a בכור bechor for inheritance
because it's the first viable one. וחכמים אומרים עד שיהיה בו מצורת
אדם. vechachamim omrim ad sheyehei bo mitzuras adam. It has to have
a human form. If it's not a human form it doesn't even
affect פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Right it's not anything that comes out
of the woman's womb if it's not if it's not considered developed
enough let's say under forty days or in this case was completely
misshapen so it's not considered to be human regardless of whether it
actually is human.
Even emerged alive? Anyway that does not affect the status even for
פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. It doesn't affect the פטר רחם Peter Rechem
status. Now here are the following cases where it is considered human
even though it is very unformed or very
misformed but still considered human. המפלת סנדל Hamapal sandal like a sandal,
like you know a sandal is basically just one, you know, so
basically it's a fetus that the limbs are not differentiated, it's like
just one clump essentially
או שליה או שפיר o shilya o shfiyr or
the embryonic sac, placenta, or the actual like, you know שפיר shfiyr
is the actual sort of fetus itself מרוקם merukam that is to
some degree, some degree formed, the Gemara will, the Gemara talks about
what degree of forming but not the Gemara here, Gemara נדה, Niddah,
but basically the sense is 40 days developed, let's leave it at
that for now. ויצא מחותך Veyatzeh mechutach even if a child was
because the woman
was concern she was going to die in childbirth so it had
to be dismembered, the fetus, okay הבא אחריהם Habah achareihem
anyone after these. So basically these are all examples about human fetuses
that were not viable or not alive, so therefore the second child
is not a פטר רחם Peter Rechem but is still a בכור
לנחלה. Bechor Lenachala. It is still the first viable child. So the
second one is a firstborn for the inheritance because it's the first
viable, ואין בכור לכהן, ve'ein bechor lakohen, but not for the כהן
Kohen because it is not the first one out of the womb.
So that's category number one. Now we're going to do category number
two which is בכור לכהן Bechor Lakohen and not for inheritance. מי
שלא היו לו בנים ונשא אשה שביכרה. Mi shelo hayu lo banim
venasa isha shebiker. So let's say a person
had no children yet but he married a woman who already had
children. So again it's the first for the man, not the first
for the woman. So that's going to be a בכור לנחלה Bechor
Lenachala and not לכהן. Lakohen.
ילדה ועודה שפחה Yaleda veodah shifcha or let's say now how about
if her children were that this woman had were before she was
Jewish? She had children while she was a slave and then she
was freed ונשתחררה venishtachara או עובדת כוכבים ונתגיירה, o ovedet kochavim venitgeira,
okay משבאה לישראל
ילדה misheba'ah l'Yisrael yaleda
and now she had children now that she's Jewish. So בכור לנחלה
Bechor Lenachala again if it's the man's first child, okay, so it's
a בכור לנחלה, Bechor Lenachala, but it's not the woman's first biological
child even though it's her first Jewish child, nevertheless אין בכור לכהן,
ein bechor lakohen, not a בכור לכהן. Bechor Lakohen. So by בכור
לכהן Bechor Lakohen you go by the woman's first child and by
נחלה Nachala you go by the man's. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר Rabbi
Yose Haglili omer בכור לנחלה ולכהן. Bechor Lenachala ulakohen. No
he even if the firstborn for כהן Kohen. even though it's not
the woman's
first biological child, it is her first Jewish child שנאמר פטר רחם
בישראל. shenemar Peter Rechem beYisrael. It is the first one that comes
out of the womb when he is Jewish. Okay, so if he
had biological children beforehand but not as a Jew they would not
affect according to him the status for the כהן.
Kohen So יצחק Yitzchak was the first?
You mean because
you consider שרה Sarah Jewish you consider אברהם Avraham Jewish? Yeah, so
we won't get into that was he adopted somebody? I'm not having
those discussions now, we are finishing this משנה mishna עד שיפטרו רחם
בישראל ad sheyifteru rechem Yisrael has to be the coming out as
a Jew. So that is בכור לכהן Bechor Lakohen goes
by נחלה Nachala goes by the man's first child, by כהן Kohen
goes by the woman, and by כהן it has to be viable,
what, by inheritance it has to be the first viable child. Now
מי שהיו לו בנים ונשא אשה שלא ילדה. Mi shehayu lo banim
venasa isha shelo yaleda. The reverse. A man had children and he
married a woman who had yet to give birth, so it's her
first child not his. That's going to be a בכור לכהן Bechor
Lakohen and not for inheritance.
נתגיירה מעוברת נשתחררה מעוברת. Nitgeira me'uberet nishtachara me'uberet. Let's say she was
pregnant and then she converted or she was a slave and she
was freed. So what's the story there? Why is that? That's going
to be a בכור לכהן Bechor Lakohen because when the child came
out she was Jewish, but it's not בכור לנחלה Bechor Lenachala because
of the principle of קטן שנולד דמי, Katan shenolad dami, right, that
whatever he is, that when he converted was the fetus, he didn't
have any relationship to his past history. So who the father was
is irrelevant, right, in terms of the issue of inheritance because he
has a new, he's a new, he's not considered anymore related to
the original biological father. Okay, so in those
cases וילדה היא. veyalda hi. Okay וילדה. veyalda. So in those cases
it's going to be a בכור bechor for the פדיון הבן Pidyon
HaBen but not for inheritance. It's either not the father's first child
or in the case of conversion not related to the father. Now
היא וכהנת היא ולויים היא ואשה שכבר ילדה. Hi vekohenet hi veleviyah
hi ve'isha shekvar yaleda. Let's say there was a confusion whose child
it was and the second, so she gave birth to a child,
it was her first child, it would be a בכור לכהן Bechor
Lakohen and for inheritance, but now it got mixed up with another
woman's child and this other woman's child there would not have been
a מצוה of פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen why, for the other woman
it wasn't her first child or she was Or she was a
בת כהן bat kohen or a בת לוי. bat levi. Okay, so
this infant got mixed up. One of them have מצוה of פדיון
הבן, pidyon haben, one of them does not. What do you do
in that case? ובכן מי שלא שהתה לאחר בעלה שלשה חדשים, Uvchen
mi shelo shasa leachar ba'ala shelosha chodashim, a woman's husband died and
she remarried within three months, which she's not supposed to do. And
then you don't know if this child comes from the first husband
or the second husband. So that type of a case, you don't
know who the father is for him to inherit, but you do
know that the child is still this woman's firstborn and he has
a מצוה of פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. ונישאת וילדה ואיני יודע אם
בן תשעה לראשון אם בן שבעה לאחרון, Venisais veyalda ve'eini yodeia im
ben tisha larishon im ben shiva la'acharon, in all those cases, בכור
לכהן ואינו בכור לנחלה. bechor lacohen ve'eino bechor lenachala. Now let's just
unpack that. Why is it not a בכור לנחלה? bechor lenachala? It's
not a בכור לנחלה bechor lenachala because in all those cases that
the child got mixed up, or you don't know first father or
the second, first husband or the second husband, he can't inherit because
inheritance is a civil case, it's דיני ממונות, dinei mamonus, and everybody
says, you're not getting with me and the other brothers, we're assuming
that the other guy's your father. And then he goes to the
other father's, goes, you're not our brother, you're their brother. And he
can't prove whose son he is, so he's not going to get
any inheritance. Why is he a בכור bechor for פדיון הבן? pidyon
haben? He's a בכור bechor for פדיון הבן pidyon haben because I
know that my son, you know, is חייב chayav in פדיון הבן.
pidyon haben. I just don't know which of these two babies is
my son. But I know my son is חייב chayav in פדיון
הבן. pidyon haben. So I do a פדיון הבן pidyon haben based
on whichever one of these is my son, I'm doing the פדיון
הבן pidyon haben for him, that one. So there still has to
be a פדיון הבן pidyon haben done, but because he can't prove
whose father he is, he's practically, he really is a בכור לנחלה,
bechor lenachala, but he can't prove it, so he's practically not going
to be able to get any inheritance. Okay, to be continued.